<chapter id="yamcs-pp-simulation">
<title>Yamcs PP Simulation</title>
<para>The Yamcs PP Simulation user interface allows to browse a library of scenarios, and select the one that should be played by the Yamcs PP Simulation Provider.</para>


<section><title>Installing</title>

	<section><title>Dependencies</title>
	<variablelist>
	    <varlistentry><term>OS</term>
			<listitem>Linux or Windows, 32bit or 64bit</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	    
	    <varlistentry><term>Java runtime (JRE)</term>
			<listitem>>= version 1.6</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	</section>

	<section><title>Installation</title>
		<para>The Yamcs PP Simulation is delivered as part of an archived client tools package. The package does not need to be installed, just extracted to a suitable location. The tools can be run from the extracted location using starting scripts found in the <filename>bin/</filename> folder.</para>
	</section>

	<section><title>Updating</title>
		<para>Updated applications are made available as an archived client tools package. This should be extracted into its own folder, separate to any previous installation. The configuration files in <filename>etc/</filename> can be copied from a previous installation into the new installation.</para>
	</section>
	
	<section><title>Removing</title>
		<para>To remove an installation, delete the extracted folder.</para>
	</section>
</section>

<section><title>Enable PP Simulation Data Link</title>
   <para>In order to play simulation scenarios, it is needed to add a SimulationPpProvider to the PP Providers list of the Yamcs instance.</para>
   <para>Below is config example that should be added in the config file of the yamcs instance (yamcs.instance.yaml):</para>
   <screen>
     ppProviders:
           - class: org.yamcs.simulation.SimulationPpProvider
             stream: pp_realtime
             args: {simulationDataPath: "/opt/yamcs/etc/simulation.xml"}
   </screen>
</section>


<section><title>Yamcs PP Simulation User interface</title>

   <para>The Yamcs PP Simulation is started with the command 
   <command>./yamcs-pp-simulation.sh</command> or <command>yamcs-pp-simulation.bat</command></para>
   <para>After the startup, the menu entry <guimenu>Options->Directories</guimenu> has to be used to select:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>the "scenario library" path to a local directory containing Xml scenario files.</listitem>
     <listitem>the "running scenario target" to the file that specified in the yamcs config file (<command>yamcs.instance.yaml</command>) for parameter <command>simulationDataPath</command></listitem>      
   </itemizedlist>


    <figure><title>Yamcs PP Simulation user interface</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject> <imagedata width="100%" fileref="images/yamcs-pp-simulation.png" format="PNG"/> </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>To run a scenario in Yamcs:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>Browse to the desired scenario in the Library section</listitem>
        <listitem>Click the 'Select' button</listitem>
        <listitem>(re)Enable the simulation data link from Yamcs Monitor</listitem>       
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The simulation link in Yamcs Monitor should be disable and enable again to take into account the new simulation scenario. Below is a picture of the Yamcs Monitor with the simulation data link enabled:</para>
    <figure><title>Simulation PP Link in Yamcs Monitor</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject> <imagedata width="100%" fileref="images/yamcs-pp-simulation-monitor.png" format="PNG"/> </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </figure>
</section>

<section><title>Scenario file format</title>

    <para>The scenarios are defined in XML files. They follow the definition of the file:
    <command>scenario_data.xsd</command>, available in the Yamcs sources, at location <command>yamcs/yamcs-simulation/src/main/resources/org/yamcs/xsd</command>.</para>
    <para>Examples of scenario files can be found in Yamcs sources, at location <command>yamcs/yamcs-simulation/src/test/resources</command>.</para>
</section>
</chapter>
